My foolish younger brother...
(イタチ)愚かなる弟よ。
Wow, Onii-san!
((すげぇよ 兄さん！
You nailed every target, even the one
in the blind spot behind the rock!
岩の裏の
死角の的にも ど真ん中だ！
All right, my turn!
よ～し！ オレだって…。
Sasuke.
サスケ そろそろ帰ろう。
It's time to go.
新しい手裏剣術
教えてくれるって言っただろ！
You said that you would teach me
a new shuriken jutsu.
I have an important mission tomorrow
that I must prepare for.
明日は
ちょっと大事な任務があって➡
その準備がある。
兄さんのウソつき…。
You're a liar...
Sorry, Sasuke.
許せ サスケ。 また 今度な。
イテッ！
- Maybe some other time.
- Ow!
Nii-san, watch this!
兄さん 見てて！
(コラ！ ムチャしたら…))
Hey!
Don't be reckless...
i realise the screaming pain
hearing loud in my brain
but i'm going straight ahead with the scar
I should just get over it and I should just stop feeling it
wasurete shimaeba ii yo kanjinaku nacchaeba ii
and so I covered my grazed heart
surimuita kokoro ni futa wo shitan da
I don't care if I'm hurt 'cause I don't feel pain anymore
kizutsuitatte heki da yo mou itami wa nai kara ne
all while you limped on while dragging your feet behind you
sono ashi wo hikizuri nagara mo
I had lost sight of myself
miushinatta jibun jishin ga
which had crumbled loudly to the ground
oto wo taete kuzureteita
but then I realised it was just the sound of the wind...
kizukeba kaze no oto dake ga
I came here to tell you something following my deep scars
tsutae ni kita yo kizuato wo tadotte
before I am completely crushed by this vast world
sekai ni oshitsubusarete shimau mae ni
do you remember that sky of tears
oboeteru kana namida no sora wo
that pain protected you for me
ano itami ga kimi no koto wo mamotte kureta
that pain is always protecting you
sono itami ga itsumo kimi wo mamotterunda
can you hear me so am i
The Longest Moment...
((足首 ひねったヤツが
何 笑ってる？
How come the one who twisted his ankle
is the one laughing?
もしかして 楽しよう と
してるだけじゃないのか？
Was it on purpose
so I'd carry you?
違うよ。 オレも 明日から
アカデミーだと思うと 嬉しくて。
No. I'm just happy 'cuz tomorrow
I'll be starting the academy too.
(これで ちょっとは
兄さんに追いつけるからさ))
Maybe now,
I can catch up to you a little.
((イタチ 覚悟は決まったのか？
Itachi... Have you made up your mind?
お前の覚悟が決まらぬなら
我々が手を下すまで。
If not, then we will act instead--
それは お待ちください。
No, please wait.
事が動き出してからでは
すべてが手遅れになる。
It will be too late
once things start to move...
事態は切迫しているのだ。
The situation is dire!
(わかっています。
必ず けりは この手で…))
I realize that...
I shall settle this with my own hands.
((フガク : なんだと!?
What?!
明日が どんな日か
お前も知っているだろう！
Do you know
what day tomorrow is?!
(フガク)お前は
自分の立場がわかっていない！
You don't understand
your own position!
オレは 明日 任務につく。
(フガク)何の任務だ？
I'm setting out on a mission tomorrow.
What kind of mission?
それは言えない。 極秘任務だ。
I can't tell you...
It's a top-secret mission.
イタチ お前は 一族と里の中枢を繋ぐ
パイプ役でもあるのだ。
Itachi... You also serve
as the Uchiha clan's pipeline
to the Village nerve center.
それは わかってるな？
You know that, don't you?
あぁ…。
Yes...
それを よく肝に銘じておけ。
Keep that well in mind.
(そして 明日の会合には来い))
And come to tomorrow's assembly!
((父さんは
兄さんのことばっかりだ。
Father only cares about you,
Nii-san...
オレが うとましいか？
You probably hate me, huh?
別にいいさ。
It's all right...
忍ってのは
人に憎まれて生きてくのが➡
It's a fact that ninja
go through life being hated.
道理ってもんだからな。
そ… そんなふうには…。
That's not how I feel...
フフフ… 優秀ってのも考えものさ。
Being the best isn't all
it's cracked up to be...
力を持てば 孤立もするし
傲慢にもなってくる。
If you have power,
you become alienated and also arrogant.
最初は 望まれ
求められていたとしてもだ。
Even if you're coveted and
sought after at first.
ただ お前とオレは
唯一無二の兄弟だ。
But, we only have each other
as siblings.
お前の越えるべき壁として
オレは お前とともにあり続けるさ。
I'm always going to be there for you,
even if it's only as an obstacle
for you to overcome.
たとえ 憎まれようともな。
Even if you do hate me...
それが 兄貴ってもんだ。
That's what big brothers are for.
(ヤシロ)イタチは いるか!?
Is Itachi here?!
(ヤシロ)出てこい！ 話がある。
We need to talk. Come out!
なんです？ 皆さん お揃いで。
What brings you all here?
昨日の会合に出なかったヤツが
２人 いる。
There were two people who didn't show up
at yesterday's assembly.
(イナビ)お前は なぜ 来なかった!?
Why didn't you come?
暗部に入り いろいろな面倒ごとに
駆り出されるのは わかる。
We understand that joining
the Anbu Black Ops means
being pushed to do all sorts
of petty assignments.
お前の父上も そう言い
何かと かばってはいる。
Your father has said as much
and tries to defend you.
しかし 我々は
お前を特別扱いする気はない！
But we have no intention of
giving you special treatment.
わかりました。
以後 気をつけましょう。
I understand.
I shall be more careful hereafter.
そろそろ お引き取りを。
Now, I'm going to have to
ask you to leave.
そうだな。
All right.
だが その前に もう少しだけ
聞きたいことがあってな。
But before that, we'd like to ask you
a bit more about something.
ゆうべ 南賀ノ川に身投げした
うちはシスイについてだ。
It's about Uchiha Shisui
who died after throwing himself into
the Nakano River last night.
たしか お前は シスイを
実の兄のように慕っていたな。
As I recall, you looked up to him like
an older brother, didn't you?
そうですか。
I see...
最近では まったく
会ってなかったが… 残念です。
I hadn't seen him recently...
That's too bad.
で… 我々 警務部隊は 全力で
捜査に乗り出すことを決定した。
And we, the Police Force, have decided
to launch an all-out investigation.
捜査？
Investigation?!
これが シスイの書いた遺書だ。
This is the will Shisui left.
筆跡の鑑定は済んでる。
間違いなく 本人が書いたものだ。
The handwriting analysis shows
that it is unmistakably his.
(イタチ)他殺の線がないなら
何の捜査ですか？
If there are no signs of foul play,
why investigate at all?
写輪眼を使える者なら
筆跡のコピーなど たやすいがな。
Someone who uses Sharingan would
be able to make a perfect copy.
(ヤシロ)うちは一の手だれ
瞬身のシスイと恐れられた男だ。
"I HAVE WEARIED OF DUTY.
AS IT IS, THE UCHIHA HAS NO FUTURE. NEITHER DO
I... I CAN NO LONGER FOLLOW THE "PATH."
The most talented of all our clan,
feared as Shisui the Teleporter...
一族のためなら どんな任務でも
先立ってやる男だった。
He was a man who took on any mission
for the sake of the clan.
そんな男が こんなものを残して
自殺するとは考えづらい。
It's hard to believe that someone like that
would kill himself,
leaving this behind.
見た目や思い込みだけで➡
You shouldn't judge people
by their appearance,
人を判断しないほうが
いいですよ。
or by your own preconceptions.
とりあえず
その遺書を お前に預ける。
Anyway, we'll leave his will with you.
それを持って お前から
暗部にも捜査協力を要請しろ。
Take it to the Anbu
and request their cooperation
in the investigation!
了解しました。
Understood...
手がかりが出てくるといいがな。
Let's hope we get a lead on this soon.
(イタチ)もっと直接的に
言ったら どうです？
Why don't you just come out
and say it?
オレを疑ってるってわけか？
You all suspect me, right?
ああ そうだ。 クソガキ。
Yeah, that's right.
You little punk!
さっきも言ったはずだ。
Like I said earlier,
見た目や思い込みだけで
人を判断しないほうがいい。
appearances and preconception
aren't going to tell you anything.
オレの気が長いと勝手に判断し
タカをくくるからだ。
You assume that I'm very patient
and underestimate me...
一族 一族…。
The clan... the clan...
そういうアンタらは
その器の大きさを量り違え➡
You keep harping on it,
mistaking the size of that vessel
and underestimating the size of mine.
オレの器の深さを知らぬから
今 そこに はいつくばってる。
That's why you're here now, groveling.
シスイは…
最近のお前を監視していた。
Shisui had been monitoring you lately.
暗部に入って半年。
It's been six months since
you joined the Anbu,
最近のお前の
言動のおかしさは目に余る。
but your recent words and actions
have been intolerable.
お前は いったい何を考えて…。
Just what are you thinking?
組織に執着し
一族に執着し 名に執着する。
This attachment to the organization,
to the clan, to one's name...
それは 己を制約し
己の器を決める忌むべきこと。
Such attachments put a limit on
one's vessel and should be shunned.
そして いまだ見ぬ知らぬものを
恐れ憎しむ 愚かしきこと！
To fear and hate things that
we cannot see or understand as yet
(フガク)やめろ イタチ！
is totally ridiculous!
Stop! Itachi!
いい加減にしろ。
どうしたというのだ？ いったい。
That's enough...
What is going on with you?
イタチ… お前 最近 少し変だぞ。
Itachi...
You haven't been yourself lately.
(イタチ)何も おかしくない。
I'm perfectly sane.
自分の役割を果たしている。
それだけだ。
I'm carrying out my duties.
That's all I'm doing.
じゃあ なぜ 昨晩は来なかった？
Then why didn't you come last night?
高みに近づくため…。
In order to elevate myself higher...
なんの話だ？
What are you talking about?
オレの器は
このくだらぬ一族に絶望している。
My vessel is dismayed at
this foolish clan!
一族などと
ちっぽけなものに執着するから➡
Adhering to this clan...
and petty things...
本当に大切なものを見失う。
makes you lose sight of
what's truly important.
本当の変化とは 規制や制約➡
Real change won't come about when
you're bound by regulations and limitation...
予感や想像の枠に
収まりきっていては できない。
when you're satisfied with
premonition and guesses.
傲慢なことを！
もう いい…。
Such arrogance!
Enough.
それ以上 くだらぬ戯れ言を
言うなら 牢につなぐ。
Say another word and
we'll throw you in prison!
(フガク)さあ どうするんだ？
So, what will you do?!
もう我慢できません！
隊長 拘束の命令を!!
I've had enough!
Captain, give us the order to arrest him!
兄さん… もう やめてよ!!
Nii-san! Please stop!
シスイを殺したのは オレじゃない。
I did not kill Shisui...
けれど 数々の失言は 謝ります。
申し訳ありません。
But I apologize for the words
I have spoken...
I'm truly sorry.
最近 暗部での任務に忙殺されて
少し疲れていたようだな。
You've been working too hard on
your Anbu Black Ops missions,
and I think you're a little tired.
隊長！
But Captain!
暗部は 火影様の直轄部隊。
The Anbu Black Ops is under
the direct orders of the Hokage.
いくら 我々 警務部隊でも
捕捉状がなければ逮捕できない。
Without an arrest warrant,
we cannot detain him.
それに イタチのことは
このオレが 責任を持って監視する。
I will take full responsibility over Itachi
and keep an eye on him.
頼む。
You have my word.
わかりました。
Very well, sir.
入るぞ イタチ。
Let's go inside, Itachi.
(ミコト)イタチ…
食事 ここに置いておくわね。
Itachi...
I'll leave your meal here.
お仕事が忙しいのでしょうけど➡
I know you're busy with work,
but do join us for meals once in a while.
たまには家族で
一緒に食事をとりましょう。
ありがとう 母さん。
Thank you...
Mother.
《居残って 手裏剣 投げてたら
だいぶ遅くなっちゃったな》
I stayed back to practice
throwing shuriken
and now I'm totally late.
《今 なんかいたような気が…》
I had a feeling
there was someone there...
なんだよ… これ…。
What is this?!
父さん！ 母さん！
Father! Mother!
兄さん！ 父さんと母さんが…
なんで？ どうして!?
Nii-san!
Father and Mother are...!
いったい 誰が こんなこと…。
Why? What happened?!
Who would do such a thing?!
愚かなる弟よ。
Foolish younger brother...
万華鏡写輪眼！
Mangekyo Sharingan!
((さすが オレの子だ。
(ミコト)あなたのことばかり
話してるのよ お父さん))
He's worthy of being my son.
Your father only talks about you.
うわ～っ!!
やめて 兄さん！
こんなの見せないで!!
Stop it, Nii-san!
Why are you showing me all of this?!
どうして…。
Why...?
どうして 兄さんが…。
Why did you do this?
己の器を量るためだ。
To measure my abilities...
器を… 量る？ それだけ？
Measure your abilities?
That's all?
それだけのために
みんなを殺したっていうの？
Just for that...
you... killed everyone?
それが重要なのだ。
It is of great importance.
(うっ… ううっ…))
((ウソだ… こんなの
兄さんじゃない。 だって…。
It's a lie!
This isn't like you, Nii-san...
お前が望むような兄を
演じ続けてきたのは➡
It can't be...!
I acted like the older brother
you desired...
お前の器を確かめるためだ。
in order to measure your vessel.
お前は オレの器を
確かめるための相手になる。
You will become a rival to measure
my vessel against...
そういう可能性を秘めている。
お前は オレを
うとましく思い 憎んでいた。
You have that hidden potential.
You've been jealous of me
and resented me.
このオレを超えることを
望み続けていた。
You've harbored hopes
of surpassing me.
だからこそ生かしてやる。
オレのために。
That is why I am allowing you to live.
For my sake...
お前は オレと同じ
万華鏡写輪眼を開眼しうる者だ。
Like me, you will awaken the powers
of the Mangekyo Sharingan.
ただし それには条件がある。
However, on one condition...
最も親しい友を殺すことだ。
You must kill... your closest friend!
このオレのようにな。
As I did...
あれ… 兄さんが…。
Then... you...
兄さんが シスイさんを…。
そのおかげで
この眼を手に入れた。
You killed Shisui-san?
As a result, I possess this "eye".
南賀ノ神社 本堂。
その右奥から７枚目の畳の下に
一族秘密の集会場がある。
In the main hall in Nakano Shrine
beneath the seventh tatami mat from
the inner right side
is the clan's hidden meeting room.
そこには うちは一族の瞳術が
本来 なんのために存在するか➡
There you will find the record of
the Uchiha Clan's Visual Jutsu
その本当の秘密が記されている。
and its true purpose.
お前が開眼すれば オレを含め➡
万華鏡写輪眼を扱う者は
３人になる。
If you awaken the Mangekyo Sharingan,
there will be three, including myself,
who possess its powers.
そうなれば フフッ…
お前を生かしておく意味もある。
Then...
there will be meaning
in letting you live.
今のお前など 殺す価値もない。
There is no value in killing you now...
愚かなる弟よ。
my foolish little brother.
このオレを殺したくば 恨め 憎め。
If you wish to kill me,
resent me, hate me,
そして 醜く生きのびるがいい。
and survive... in obscurity.
逃げて逃げて
生に しがみつくがいい。
Run... keep running...
(そしていつかオレと
同じ眼を持ってオレの前に来い))
and cling to life.
Then one day, come before me
with the same eye that I possess.
その写輪眼
お前はどこまで見えている？
That Sharingan...
How much can you actually see?
どこまで見えてるだと？
今のオレの
この眼に見えているのは➡
How much can I see with these?
イタチ アンタの死にざまだ。
What I'm seeing right now, Itachi...
is your death.
オレの死にざまか。
My death, huh?
では…。
Well then...
再現してみろ。
make it happen.
千鳥。
Chidori!
《千鳥 流し！》
Chidori Stream!
強くなったな。
You've become... strong.
最後に イタチ。
アンタに聞きたかったことがある。
Itachi... I have one last thing to ask...
((イタチ : 強くなったな。))
You've become... strong
前とまったく同じセリフにカラス。
The same line as before...
and the bird...
お得意の幻術で茶番か？
何が知りたい。
Another farce with
your special genjutsu?
最後ではないが 聞いてやる。
What do you want to know?
It's not over, but I'll hear you out.
もう一度言う。
I'll say it once more...
幻術。
最後にアンタに聞きたいことがある。
Genjutsu...
I have one last thing to ask...
そう言ったんだよ クソヤロウ！
オレの質問に答えろ。
That's what I said, you bastard!
答えるまで その胸の痛みは続く。
Answer my question.
急所はわざと外したか。
That pain in your chest won't
subside until you answer.
アンタはあのとき言った。
So you purposely missed a vital spot...
((お前が開眼すれば オレを含め➡
You said back then...
万華鏡写輪眼を
扱う者は３人になる。
If you awaken
the Mangekyo Sharingan,
there will be three, including myself,
who possess its powers.
(そうなれば フフッ
お前を生かしておく意味もある))
Then...
３人目 もう１人の写輪眼とは…
うちは一族とは誰だ？
there will be meaning
in letting you live.
The third person...
The other one with a Sharingan...
なぜ そんなことを気にする？
Who in the Uchiha Clan is it?
Why... the curiosity about such a thing?
アンタの次に ソイツを殺す。
そのためだ。
I'm going to kill him after you.
That's why.
殺す？
一族を皆殺しにしたあのタイミングで➡
Kill?
When you killed off the entire clan,
アンタは もう１人の存在を口にした。
you mentioned the existence
of another person.
アンタが殺さなかった うちは。
ソイツはつまり
協力者だったってことだ。
So that Uchiha member you didn't kill
was a co-conspirator.
いくらアンタでも 警務部隊を
１人でやれるはずがない。
Even you could not kill
the entire Police Force alone.
ちゃんと気づいたか。
誰だ？
So you figured it out...
Who is it?!
うちはマダラだ。
It's Uchiha Madara...
((その瞳力と
わし以上にまがまがしいチャクラ。
With that vision and chakra
more ominous than my own...
かつての うちはマダラと同じだな。
It's just like... Uchiha Madara,
from long ago...
(知るかよ そんなヤツ))
Hell if I know... that person.
うちはマダラ？
Uchiha... Madara?!
木ノ葉隠れ創始者の１人。
万華鏡写輪眼を
最初に開眼した男だ。
One of the founders
of Hidden Leaf Village...
The man who first possessed
the Mangekyo Sharingan.
you are next to me
omae ga tonari ni iru
you are laughing
omae ga waratte iru
you seem so happy
omae ga ureshisou de
so I laughed too
ore mo waratta
you were so innocent and naive
omae wa mujaki datta
you were so kindhearted
omae wa yasashi katta
you sometimes cried
omae wa tokidoki naki
so I was troubled
ore wa komatta
who did I ask strength from at that time
dare yori tsuyosa wo motometa ano koro
since that was my one and only weakness
ore no tatta hitotsu no yowasa ga
that was you
omae datta
and it was you
omae datta n da
I want to see you
aitai
overnights
yoru wo koete
over time
toki wo koete
I want to see you now
ima aitai
Next Episode
Uchiha Madara...
The only man to uncover the other secret
of the Mangekyo Sharingan.
(グレイ)ラクサス…。
If that's Madara,
the founder of the Hidden Leaf,
(ルーシィ)ラクサスが 来てくれた。
he should be long dead.
(ウェンディ)この人が マスターの…。
Who would believe such a story?
Madara is alive...
It's up to you whether you believe
that or not.
(ハデス)こやつ マカロフの血族か。
Next time on Naruto Shippuden: "The Light & Dark  of the Mangekyo Sharingan"
The Light & Dark
of the Mangekyo Sharingan
Let me tell you a little about the past...